<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sober ansvver, to a serious question. Propounded by Mr. G. Firmin minister of the church in Shalford in Essex. viz. Whether the ministers of England are bound, by the Word of God, to baptise the children of all such parents, which say, they believe in Jesus Christ: but are grosly ignorant, scandalous in their conversation, scoffers at godliness, and refuse to submit to church-discipline, the negative is not sufficiently defended. Which may serve also as an appendix to the diatribe with Mr. Hooker, lately published, concerning the baptisme of infants, of parents not confœderate. By Daniel Cavvdrey pastour of the church at Great Billing in Northampton-shire. Licensed, printed, and entred, according to order.</title>
            <author>Cawdrey, Daniel, 1588-1664.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 76 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78433</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1636</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E683_23</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206820</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865926</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865926</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118181</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78433)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118181)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 105:E683[23])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sober ansvver, to a serious question. Propounded by Mr. G. Firmin minister of the church in Shalford in Essex. viz. Whether the ministers of England are bound, by the Word of God, to baptise the children of all such parents, which say, they believe in Jesus Christ: but are grosly ignorant, scandalous in their conversation, scoffers at godliness, and refuse to submit to church-discipline, the negative is not sufficiently defended. Which may serve also as an appendix to the diatribe with Mr. Hooker, lately published, concerning the baptisme of infants, of parents not confœderate. By Daniel Cavvdrey pastour of the church at Great Billing in Northampton-shire. Licensed, printed, and entred, according to order.</title>
                  <author>Cawdrey, Daniel, 1588-1664.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 31, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Christopher Meredith at the sign of the Crane in Pauls Church-yard.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to "A serious question stated" by Giles Firmin and to "The covenant of grace opened" by Thomas Hooker.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Decemb. 10".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hooker, Thomas, 1586-1647. --  Covenant of grace opened --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Firmin, Giles, 1614-1697. --  Serious question stated --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Baptism --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Infant baptism --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118181:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Sober ANSWER, TO A Serious Queſtion. PROPOUNDED <hi>By</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>G. Firmin</hi> Miniſter of the Church in <hi>Shalford</hi> in <hi>Eſſex.</hi> viz. Whether the Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> are bound, by the Word of God, to Baptiſe the children of all ſuch Parents, which ſay, they believe in Jeſus Chriſt; but are groſly Ignorant, Scandalous in their Converſation, Scoffers at Godlineſs, and refuſe to ſubmit to Church-diſcipline, The Negative is not ſufficiently defended. Which may ſerve alſo as an Appendix to the Diatribe with M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Hooker,</hi> lately publiſhed, concerning the Baptiſme of Infants, of Parents not confoederate.</p>
            <p>By DANIEL CAVVDREY Paſtour of the Church at Great <hi>Billing</hi> in <hi>Northampton-ſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Mark 10.14.</bibl>
               <p>Suffer the little children to come unto me, and forbid them not, for of ſuch is the Kingdom of God.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Licenſed, Printed, and entred, according to order.</p>
            <p>LONDON. Printed for <hi>Chriſtopher Meredith</hi> at the ſign of the <hi>Crane</hi> in <hi>Pauls Church-yard.</hi> 1652.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:118181:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:118181:2"/>
            <head>TO THE <hi>J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>DICIO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</hi> BUT Indifferent Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is (as the Reverend <hi>Authour</hi> of the Queſtion now before us, ſayes, in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry entrance of his <hi>Epiſtle</hi> to the Reader) a very ſad and uncomfortable <hi>ſtate</hi> of a diſeaſed Church, when the <hi>Phyſitians</hi> are at difference concerning the way of curing the Patient. This (as in other things, by others) is really exemplified in himſelf, and one Mr. <hi>Jeanes,</hi> in a Learned Tract of his, intitled, <q rend="inline">[<hi>The want of Church Government, no warrant for a total omiſſion of the Lords Supper</hi>]</q> who both intending the <hi>Cure</hi> of their diſeaſed flocks, go clean contrary waies to ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect it. He is ſo far from denying <hi>Children</hi> of the moſt Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous, the priviledge of Baptiſme, that he admits ſuch <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents</hi> to the Lords Supper, pleading the neceſsity of that Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, and his own want of <hi>power</hi> to amend, or keep them away. Our <hi>Authour,</hi> on the other ſide, not onely keeps ſuch Parents from the Lords Supper, but alſo denyes Baptiſme, the other Sacrament, to their children. The one way ſeems to
<pb facs="tcp:118181:3"/> ſome, to tend to the <hi>Prophanation</hi> of that Ordinance: The other to the <hi>diviſion,</hi> if not the deſtruction of the Church, by making all, at leaſt the greateſt part of the children of Congregations, little better then Infidels. And which of of theſe two wayes of <hi>Cure,</hi> is beſt, or worst, is hard to ſay. I ſhall ſay nothing at preſent of the former, but (with leave) ſomething of the latter, with as much mildneſſe and meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe as I can; for he ſayes truly <q rend="inline">[<hi>He hath not ſo handled the queſtion, as to deſerve a ſharp anſwer, pag. laſt.</hi>]</q> Had he ſeen (which I conceive, he hath not) a Tract lately come forth, called <q rend="inline">[<hi>The inconſiſtency of the Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent way with Scripture, and with it ſelf</hi>]</q> he had found a <hi>Diatribe</hi> there with Reverend Mr. <hi>Hooker,</hi> about almoſt his very queſtion; which either might have preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his publication, or have given him occaſion, to alter, or enlarge his thoughts, in ſome particulars; his grounds being moſt of them taken from M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Hooker,</hi> and the anſwers and arguments against him, falling full upon his own. The diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between them is not great, if any at all. The one, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>(Hooker)</hi> requires an <hi>Explicite Covenant;</hi> to make Church members, and allows no children of the moſt know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and godly Parents, not confederate, the priviledge of bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme. The other ſeems to deny Baptiſme, onely to the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of thoſe who are <hi>groſly ignorant, ſcandalous, &amp;c.</hi> I ſay, he ſeems onely to do this: For both he ſpeaks <hi>ſuſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly</hi> ſometimes, towards an <hi>Explicite Covenant,</hi> and his queſtion, as it ſtands in <hi>terminis,</hi> (not being at all explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) if not rightly taken, may ſeem alſo to exclude the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of ſuch, as ſubmit not to <hi>Church-diſcipline,</hi> though knowing and godly. And pag. 9. of <hi>his Epiſtle,</hi> he requires expreſly (as a qualification of a member) <q rend="inline">[<hi>That he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe his ſubjection to Diſcipline</hi>]</q> which is <hi>Tanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:118181:3"/> if not the ſame, with the Independents <hi>Explicite Covenant;</hi> yet herein he is to be commended, that he is not ſo <hi>rigide</hi> as they are, in his qualification, or admiſsions of members.</p>
            <p>And ſeeing we are accidentally fallen upon the <hi>Explicite Covenant,</hi> I ſhall conſider what he ſayes of it, in his <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle;</hi> though I might refer him to the <hi>Tract</hi> aforeſaid, where it is fully handled. In pag. 16. of his <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> thus he ſpeaks <q rend="inline">[<hi>Some Miniſters ſcorn the notion, that an expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite Covenant, is the form of a Church viſible; and ſome profeſſours are ſo rigid for it, that without it, they deny all Churches</hi>]</q> of the later ſort, is <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Hoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker</hi> himſelf, (though ſometime he grant an implicite Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant ſufficient) for part 3. of his <hi>Survey</hi> pag. 11. he ſayes expreſly, <q rend="inline">[<hi>Non confoederate perſons, in their ſenſe are Non members of the Church, &amp;c.</hi>
               </q> and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly their children have no title to Baptiſme, (which is one of our <hi>Authours</hi> arguments in pag. 10. of his book, borrowed from <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Hooker part.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>p.</hi> 24.) whereby he <hi>unmembers,</hi> and <hi>unchurches</hi> all not ſo conſtituted. For my part, I ſcorn not ſuch a notion, but with <hi>Apollonius,</hi> and others, think it lawful, though not neceſſary, as the form to the being of the Church; the <hi>Impſicite</hi> being of it ſelf, confeſſed to be fully ſufficient. But I require a proof of the <hi>neceſſity</hi> of it. All that can reaſonably be ſaid, is but this, That it is very requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite and expedient, in corrupted Churches, in a time of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation,</hi> to renew the <hi>Covenant</hi> with God; and that includes the Covenant of <hi>Paſtours</hi> and <hi>Members,</hi> and of <hi>Members</hi> one with onother, <q rend="inline">[<hi>To walk with God and one another in all relations</hi>]</q> Our <hi>Authour</hi> himſelf ſeems to grant, the <hi>Implicite</hi> Covenant may ſerve to the <hi>eſſe. For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male;</hi> but then, in a manner recalls his grant again, when
<pb facs="tcp:118181:4"/> he ſayes there, <q rend="inline">[<hi>Though expliciteneſſe be not eſſential to the eſſe Formale of a Church, yet you will find it almoſt eſſential to the eſſe of a Government, &amp;c. elſe when you come to exerciſe diſcipline, you will find ſome members explicitely ſtubborn, to ſpurn the Implicite Covenant, at their heels.</hi>]</q> Truly they that are ſuch, can as well ſpurn the <hi>Explicite</hi> alſo. And in this <hi>Looſeneſſe,</hi> or rather <hi>want</hi> of Church-government, can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move from his Church, to another, and eaſe themſelves of his moſt <hi>Explicite Covenant.</hi> They (of whom he ſpeaks there) that <q rend="inline">[<hi>acknowledged diſcipline as an Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and ſaid to him, that if they had not promiſed him to ſubmit to diſcipline, he had no power over them</hi>]</q> ſpake not aright. For by the <hi>Explicite</hi> Covenant of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> they were bound Implicitely to all Gods Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, (of which this is one) and he had thereby power over them. And by the <q rend="inline">[<hi>Implicite conſent to Church-government, in that Implicite Covenant, which is in every Parochial Congregation, pag.</hi> 17.]</q> they were bou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d to him, and he had power over them, though they did not explicitely promiſe him, to ſubmit to him: yea, that Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, both general of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> and ſpecial, in joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with a Parochial Congregation, if he would improve it, and preſſe the obligation of it, upon his people, were ſufficient to perſwade them to <hi>ſubmit,</hi> and authorize him to exerciſe diſcipline upon them. <note place="margin">See Review of Survey part. 2. p. 104 &amp; 109. &amp;c.</note> But if people will be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe and obſtinate (at their perill be it) they can as eaſily caſt off the cords of his <hi>Explicite Covenant,</hi> as <hi>Sampſon</hi> did his <hi>wythes;</hi> yet pag. 17. he ſayes <q rend="inline">[<hi>How can this diſcipline be exerciſed, without a free conſent unto it, being this Church-relation, is not natural as (father and child) but free</hi>]</q> when to my apprehenſion,
<pb facs="tcp:118181:4"/> he requires an <hi>Explicite Covenant,</hi> to make or admit a member, as <hi>Independents</hi> do. The truth is, as I conceive, that <hi>relation</hi> of Chriſtians one to another, is not free, but after a ſort, natural; and flowes as natural from the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> or <hi>Regeneration,</hi> as that of father and child, brother and brother, from generation; as is more fully diſcourſed and cleared in the <hi>Tract</hi> aforeſaid. <note place="margin">Ibid pag. 125. 126. &amp;c.</note> I ſhall not trouble his <hi>Epiſtle</hi> any further, but make bold, to make ſome <hi>Animadverſions</hi> upon his book, which may ſerve as an <hi>Appendix</hi> to the <hi>Diatribe</hi> there expreſſed.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:118181:5"/>
            <head>There are lately Printed for <hi>Christopher Meredith</hi> at the <hi>Crane</hi> in <hi>Pauls Church-yard;</hi> Theſe Books.</head>
            <list>
               <item>MAſter <hi>Elton</hi> on the ten Commandments and Lords Prayer; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly burnt by the Biſhops.</item>
               <item>Doctor <hi>Dons</hi> (late <hi>Dean</hi> of <hi>Pauls</hi>) Sermon at the Lady <hi>Danvers</hi> funeral, with verſes of M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
                  <hi>George Herbert,</hi> &amp;c. 12.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Viccarſii Manuductio ad artem Rhetoricam.</hi> 12.</item>
               <item>A Letter of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Thomas Sheppards,</hi> late of New-<hi>England,</hi> ſent to <hi>R. Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lakenden</hi> of <hi>Eſſex</hi> Eſquire, removing four hindrances in Gods Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.
<list>
                     <item>Firſt, how one may be rid of an earthly carnal heart, ſold to the content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Creature.</item>
                     <item>Secondly, of a proud heart which is unwilling to ſeek after, to wait upon or to ſtoop unto the Commands of God.</item>
                     <item>Thirdly, of a ſelf-ſeeking heart that eyes it ſelf, eſpecially in the beſt duties.</item>
                     <item>Fourthly, of a ſlighty heart of Gods hands in mercies and Judgements.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>The ſtate of the Saints departed; Gods Cordial to Comfort the Saints remaining alive, a Sermon Preached at the Funeral of Miſtreſs <hi>Smithee Harlakenden,</hi> wife of <hi>William Harlakenden</hi> Eſquire, by <hi>R. Joſſelin.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Chriſtian <hi>Centurions</hi> Obſervations, advices, and Reſolutions concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning matters, <hi>Divine</hi> and <hi>Moral,</hi> by <hi>Philip Skippon,</hi> Serjeant Major Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, &amp;c. Alſo two other books formerly publiſhed by the ſame Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor. viz.
<list>
                     <item>Firſt, A Collection of Promiſes.</item>
                     <item>Secondly, A true Treaſure, or thirty holy vowes, &amp;c.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>A learned and full anſwer to a Treatiſe entituled the Vanity of childiſh Baptiſme, &amp;c. by <hi>William Cook</hi> Miniſter of <hi>Moxall</hi> in <hi>Warwickſhire.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Vindiciae Redemptionis</hi> in the Fannings and Siftings of <hi>Samuel Oates,</hi> his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition upon <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.44. by <hi>John Stalham,</hi> Paſtour of the Church at <hi>Terling</hi> in <hi>Eſſex.</hi> The Sum of a conference at <hi>Terling</hi> in <hi>Eſſex</hi> concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Infants Baptiſme.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>John Geeres</hi> Reply to Doctor <hi>Boughen,</hi> touching the Coronation oath; two books of his in defence of Infants Baptiſme, in anſwer to <hi>Mr. Tombs</hi> Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118181:5"/>
            <head>A Sober ANSVVER, TO A Serious Queſtion, Propounded and Publiſhed by <hi>G. F.</hi> Whether the Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> are bound by the Word of God to Baptize the children of all ſuch Parents which ſay, they believe in Jeſus Chriſt, but are groſly Ignorant, Scandalous in their converſations, Scoffers at Godlineſs, and refuſe to ſubmit to Church-Diſcipline?</head>
            <head type="sub">The Negative is not ſufficiently defended.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Efore I fall upon the <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> it ſelf, I ſhall take leave, a little to conſider the <hi>ſtate</hi> of the queſtion. And I deſire to be ſatisfied by the <hi>Reverend Authour,</hi> whether he intend, that all theſe quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications in his queſtion, muſt meet joyntly in one man, or he meaneth it ſeparately, and <hi>ſingly</hi> of any one of them, as ſufficient to debarr his children Baptiſme. If joyntly, that all theſe muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur, he will hardly, or very rarely find all theſe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in one man. For a man may be <hi>groſly ignorant,</hi> and yet not of a ſcandalous converſation: Or very <hi>Scanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous,</hi> and yet very knowing, or both thoſe, and yet no
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:118181:6"/> profeſſed <hi>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orner</hi> of Godlineſs. Or none of all thoſe, yet (not being convinced of the neceſſity of it) refuſe to ſubmit to <hi>Church diſcipline.</hi> If any one of theſe <hi>ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> will ſtrip him of that priviledge, then the laſt alone will do it, viz. <q rend="inline">[<hi>Refuſal to ſubmit to Church-diſcipline</hi>]</q> be a man never ſo <hi>knowing,</hi> and godly in converſation. And then, I pray, what differs he from the <hi>Independents</hi> in their <hi>Explicite</hi> Church-covenant? This is the Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of M. <hi>Hooker,</hi> whom our <hi>Author</hi> follows in moſt of his diſcourſe) <note place="margin">Survey part 3, p. 11.</note> 
               <q rend="inline">[<hi>The pinch of the queſtion lyes here, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther perſons Non-confoederate (and ſo in our ſence not members of the Church) do entitle their children to the ſeal of Baptiſme, their parents (though godly) being yet unwilling to come into Church-fellowſhip</hi>]</q> And he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves it Negatively, (as our Authour does, upon his grounds partly, and chiefly.) <note place="margin">Inconſiſt. of Independ. way &amp;c. part 3.</note> But in that ſpecial ſence, the <hi>Diatribe</hi> is ready to give him ſatisfaction: as for the preſent queſtion before us, Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> rejects it, as out of queſtion; for thus he writes; ibid. <q rend="inline">[<hi>Its not then the queſtion, whether wicked members, while they are tolerated ſinfully in the Church, they and their children may partake of the priviledges? for this is beyond queſtion, nor do I know, nor never heard it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed by any of o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rs.</hi>]</q> Had he lived till this time, he might have known, and heard of ſome of ours, (if not ſtill theirs) this queſtion negatively reſolved, and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly (though modeſtly) defended. And to ſay the truth, this queſtion ſprings from his, and ſeems a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable <hi>conſequence</hi> thereof; for if one <hi>refuſing</hi> onely to ſubmit to Church-diſcipline, loſes this priviledge of Ordinances for himſelf and his, be he never ſo knowing and godly, it ſeems very reaſonable, that ſuch
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118181:6"/> as were <hi>groſly ignorant,</hi> and <hi>ſcandalous</hi> in their converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp;c. ſhould much more juſtly be debarred the ſame. If it is ſaid, theſe are <hi>Church-members,</hi> though ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully tolerated, but ſo are not thoſe that <hi>Refuſe</hi> to come into Church-fellowſhip: I anſwer,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Theſe are <hi>Church members</hi> alſo, at leaſt of the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike</hi> Church, as more then <hi>profeſſours</hi> onely, true <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers</hi> and godly, and therefore are (we think) unjuſtly debarred the <hi>priviledg</hi> of Ordinances, for themſelves and theirs not being convinced of the <hi>neceſsity</hi> of their Church-government; as is largely diſcourſed in the place aforeſaid.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We may ſuppoſe eaſily that ſome, that were from their <hi>Infancy</hi> Church-members, yet growing up are <hi>ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled</hi> in the point of Church-diſcipline, and ſo not willing to ſubmit to it. Theſe alſo, are yet tolerated (I ſay not ſinfully) in the Church, and ſo ought not to be debar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the former Priviledges by his own principles.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Our Author, that hath ſtarted a new queſtion, (out of queſtion with M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Hooker:</hi>) oftentimes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes, (as we ſhall hear anon) that the worſt of theſe tolerated (ſinfully) while tolerated, have right to Ordinances, for themſelves and theirs. And ſo the controverſie were at an end; This principle anſwers and overthrows all his Arguments. But becauſe, the former <hi>Diatribe</hi> with M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Hooker,</hi> may receive <hi>light,</hi> and ſtrength from this <hi>Conteſt;</hi> I ſhall take into conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, thoſe things, to which little is ſaid, in that <hi>Diſcourſe,</hi> as being then out of queſtion.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> His firſt premiſe is this; <q rend="inline">[<hi>The Infant abſtracted from the Parent, gives no reaſon why it ſhould be Baptized</hi>]</q> To which (otherwiſe propounded by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Hooker</hi>) we have
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118181:7"/> anſwered already; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Diatrib.</hi> 6. <hi>p.</hi> 18<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and now explain our ſelves further, thus.</p>
            <p n="1">1. This is not rightly propoſed (of all children, or any whatſoever:) as appears, becauſe he ſpeaks indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently of the child of a <hi>Turk, Indian,</hi> or <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving together in a Pariſh, or place. A <hi>Miniſter,</hi> in ſuch a caſe, had reaſon to ask, whoſe child it is; becauſe two ſorts of the three, have no right to Baptiſme, for themſelves or theirs. But the queſtion intends to ſpeak onely of Chriſtians children; for ſo it was propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; not, whether a Miniſter at large in any place, but of <hi>England,</hi> where all are Chriſtians, and profeſſe to believe in Jeſus Chriſt: then, it is ſuppoſed he would not ask, whoſe it is in that reſpect, for it is not onely <hi>Home,</hi> but a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> born.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If he would (as he may) ask the queſtion, when a <hi>Chriſtians</hi> child is brought to be Baptized, it is not to know whether he be ignorant, ſcandalous, not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting to Church-diſcipline, &amp;c. or godly (ſuch que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions were never asked till theſe laſt <hi>over-curious</hi> dayes) but that the Parent may be preſent, to undertake for the education of the child, in the true Religion.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The ſecond premiſe, is this; <q rend="inline">[<hi>All children are Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized by virtue of the Parent, one or both, conſidered in relation to them</hi>]</q> This is Mr. <hi>Hookers</hi> ſecond premiſed concluſion; onely reſtrained to the next Parents; which is intended by our <hi>Authour</hi> alſo: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibid. p.</hi> 187.</note> To which much hath been ſaid; and now we add.</p>
            <p n="1">1. This in effect, is the ſame with the former; That the <hi>Negative;</hi> the child brings nothing of it ſelf to Baptiſme; This the <hi>Affirmative;</hi> the <hi>Parent</hi> onely gives it right thereto.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:118181:7"/>
            <p n="2">2. It takes for granted (what is denyed) theſe two things. Firſt, that there is no way to <hi>admit</hi> a childe to Baptiſme, but <hi>Parental,</hi> by virtue of, and relation to the <hi>Parent.</hi> Secondly, and that not the <hi>pro-parent,</hi> or predeceſſours, but the next <hi>Immediate</hi> Parent, which are two queſtions, the firſt whereof, he medles not with at al.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In ſtating of this ſecond premiſe, he takes occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to define a <hi>Church;</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">[<hi>A Society of viſible Saints joyned together, by way of Covenant, &amp;c.</hi>]</q> where two things are to me obſervable. 1. That he ſeems to own no <hi>Catholike</hi> Church, but a Particular Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; nor any <hi>members</hi> of a Church, but of ſuch a Church; For elſe a new queſtion may ariſe; whether a man converted to the Faith, but as yet confoederate with no particular Church, but (if of any) onely of the Catholick Church, be to be reputed a Church mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and have any right to require Baptiſme for his child. 2. He requiring an explicite Covenant to ſuch a Church, ſeems not onely to <hi>contradict</hi> himſelf, in his <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> where he grants an <hi>Implicite</hi> Covenant to be ſufficient, but alſo to <hi>un-Church</hi> moſt of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Churches, for want of this <hi>Explicite</hi> Covenant, and conſequently to agree with the <hi>Independents,</hi> as in that point, ſo in this, in denying <hi>Baptiſme</hi> to any children, but of members explicitely in Covenant.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Having premiſed thus, he infers this concluſion <q rend="inline">[<hi>upon this ground, all our Arguments againſt the Anabaptiſts ſtand; and if this be taken away, Infant Baptiſme muſt fall</hi>]</q> To which I ſay; Our arguments againſt the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> ſtand not upon this ground only; But their Arguments againſt <hi>Infant Baptiſme,</hi> ſtand upon the notion of an <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicite</hi> Covenant, to be made by every one that is Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118181:8"/> And if we had no better ground, than an <hi>Explicite</hi> Covenant, our cauſe muſt fall. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Diatrib.</hi> 6. <hi>p.</hi> 186.</note> The difference is not great: The <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> exclude children, becauſe they are not able to <hi>Covenant</hi> in perſon, in the Covenant of grace: The <hi>Independents</hi> exclude children of Parents not joyned to gether in a Church-Covenant, and ſo in their ſence no <hi>Members</hi> of a Church, as was ſaid elſewhere.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> As for that argument pag. 2. charged upon <hi>Ameſius</hi> and others; it is, (I ſuppoſe) miſtaken. For it is not brought immediately to prove childrens Baptiſme, <q rend="inline">[<hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are capable of the grace of Baptiſme; men al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo being but meer Patients, in the firſt receiving of it</hi>]</q> but by way of anſwer to an objection made againſt it by the <hi>Anabaptists.</hi> They plead that children have not, nor are capable of the grace of Faith and Repentance, <hi>ergo</hi> not to be baptized: Our <hi>Divines</hi> deny the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence upon this ground. They are <hi>capable</hi> of grace, as well as men of years, both being alike but <hi>Patients</hi> in the firſt receiving of Grace; therefore that can be no barr to their Baptiſme. But enough of that.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> It is not properly ſpoken, pag. 3. to ſay, <q rend="inline">[<hi>The Mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of that command (to</hi> Abraham <hi>to circumciſe his ſeed, with himſelf) ſtands thus, that the children of Believers muſt have the Imitating ſeal.</hi>]</q> The Analogy indeed ſtands fair, under ſeveral diſpenſations of the ſame Covenant; that, as circumciſion then, ſo <hi>Baptiſme</hi> how, belongs to believers and their children, unleſs God <hi>reveal</hi> himſelf to the contrary, which concerns <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> to prove, by <hi>expreſſe</hi> Scripture, (as he ſayes) which they can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver do. Nay the contrary is evidently continued, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.38. &amp;c. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14. &amp;c. The ſeed is holy by the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents.</hi> If he ſhould plead a <hi>Morality</hi> in that command,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118181:8"/> the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> would eaſily deny it, and put the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference; there was expreſſe <hi>Command</hi> for childrens <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> not ſo for their Baptiſme; It is enough it can be proved by <hi>conſequence</hi> from Scripture.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Concerning the queſtion about <hi>predeceſſours</hi> giving right to childrens Baptiſme, much need not to be ſaid here, It is largely diſcuſſed in the foreſaid <hi>Diatribe</hi> with Mr. <hi>Hooker,</hi> pag. 188. and afterwards. All that I ſhal ſay now, is this. 1. What <hi>England</hi> was when <hi>Auſtin</hi> came into <hi>England,</hi> we need not much enquire. For we look at <hi>England,</hi> as many years ſince reformed, we need not go to many generations paſt, there are ſome alive, that had, or have <hi>predeceſſours</hi> known to be godly, let the queſtion be of them; and two of them under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking for the Chriſtian education of the childe. And though it be true, that ſome people received the Goſpel after the example of their Kings, and were Baptized for <hi>company</hi> (as <hi>Simon Magus</hi> it ſeems was) and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing it was but in outward profeſſion onely, yet that was ſufficient to give them <hi>right</hi> to Baptiſme, for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and theirs, and conſequently they were a true <hi>Church,</hi> though not a perfect and pure <hi>Church.</hi> For my part, I ſhould not plead that promiſe in the ſecond Commandment, <hi>ſhewing mercy to thouſands, &amp;c.</hi> but rather that to <hi>Abraham,</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">[<hi>I am thy God, and the God of thy ſeed</hi>]</q> which, whoever will <hi>reſtrain</hi> to the next ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration onely, it concerns him to prove, by <hi>expreſſe Scripture,</hi> (as he required above in a like caſe, of <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts</hi>) that God is not the God of the ſeed of a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Chriſtian, in a <hi>ſecond</hi> or <hi>third</hi> generation, but onely of the <hi>firſt;</hi> which I believe he cannot do.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> It may truely be ſaid; Though the <hi>immediate</hi> Parent
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118181:9"/> godly, do give right to his child for <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> yet if that <hi>child</hi> growing up, prove <hi>Scandalous,</hi> his Parents godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe doth not give him now right to the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> becauſe he himſelf puts in a <hi>bar,</hi> to keep him from the <hi>Supper;</hi> the reaſon is, becauſe more is required of him for the <hi>Supper,</hi> than for Baptiſme. But then ſayes he; <q rend="inline">[<hi>If ſo, why doth not the Scandalous life of the Immediate Parent put a bar between the child to be Baptized, and his predeceſſours?</hi>]</q> The anſwer is, the child muſt not ſuffer for the Parents perſonal ſin. True (ſayes he) for Eternal puniſhment. But we ſay, not for Temporal or Spiritual puniſhments. He replyes; <q rend="inline">[<hi>Not indeed when it is conſidered without relation to the Parent; which it cannot in this caſe, and ſo may ſuffer by him</hi>]</q> To which we anſwer.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Jews</hi> children could no more be conſidered without <hi>relation</hi> to their Parents, than ours, yet the <hi>wickedneſſe</hi> of a <hi>Jew</hi> hindred not their Circumciſion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We muſt diſtinguiſh between the general <hi>ſtate</hi> or a Parent, and his Perſonal wickedneſſe: If his <hi>ſtate</hi> be that of an <hi>Infidel,</hi> the child ſuffers with him; but if he be for <hi>ſtate</hi> a Chriſtian, the child is born a Chriſtian, and the Parents Perſonal ſin, is not <hi>imputed</hi> to the child, to hinder his Baptiſme. It hath, beſides its <hi>relation</hi> to its Parent, a <hi>Birth-priviledge</hi> as born of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſours, and thereby may challenge the ſeal of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme.</p>
            <p n="3">3. All this proceeds upon his former <hi>ſuppoſition,</hi> that there is no way to admit children to <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> but the Parent, and that the next and Immediate Parent, which is largely confuted, in the <hi>Diatribe,</hi> chap. 2.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, all this diſcourſe is deſtroyed, by what he
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118181:9"/> often yields, <q rend="inline">[<hi>That a wicked Parent tolerated, may give right to a childs Baptiſme.</hi>]</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> His caſe, of one in <hi>Corinth</hi> converted old, having children <hi>Infidels,</hi> which have alſo children; <q rend="inline">[<hi>whether would a minister Baptize the Infants, by virtue of the Grandfather</hi>]</q> Is not our eaſe, where both father and grandfather are Chriſtians? Yet what <hi>Miniſter</hi> that underſtands himſelf, would <hi>ſcruple</hi> to Baptize the child of an <hi>Infidel</hi> Parent, ſuppoſing him either <hi>dead,</hi> or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigning his child up to the <hi>Grandfather,</hi> to be <hi>Chriſtian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like</hi> educated? All that he ſayes againſt it, is but ſome accidental <hi>inconveniences</hi> that may follow. As firſt, <q rend="inline">[<hi>The Grandfather is old, may dye quickly, before the child grow up, &amp;c.</hi>]</q> So may the <hi>Father,</hi> though a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> and never ſo godly, yea both the <hi>Parents;</hi> who then ſhall take care for it? Again <q rend="inline">[<hi>The Infidel will not let his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Baptize the child; who have moſt right over the child, the father or Grandfather?</hi>]</q> But ſuppoſe the <hi>Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del</hi> willing to give up his child to the Grandfather: what ſayes he then? That many things may fall out to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Act</hi> of Baptiſme of ſuch an <hi>Infant,</hi> is nothing to the queſtion: the queſtion is, whether it can hinder its right? If the <hi>Grandfather</hi> alſo will undertake for it, or ſome other friend, what ſayes he then? If the <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> be a Chriſtian, though the father an <hi>Infidel,</hi> yet ſhe can give a right to the childes Baptiſme: this he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes pag. 10. But the father an <hi>Infidel,</hi> will not ſuffer it to be Baptized, or if Baptized, will breed it up in his Idolatry; I ask, as he, <q rend="inline">[<hi>who hath moſt right over the child, the father or the mother?</hi>]</q> yet the child unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyably, hath right to <hi>Baptiſme</hi> by the mother. So then, there may be a <hi>right</hi> to Baptiſme, where no <hi>power</hi> to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118181:10"/> act it; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>See Diatrib. p.</hi> 188.</note> ſo it may be in the <hi>Grandfather,</hi> for ought is yet ſaid.</p>
            <p>Its true, that <hi>Aquinas</hi> ſaith, in his 8. pag. <q rend="inline">[<hi>chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Infidels are not to be Baptized, white they are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their care and power, against their wills</hi>]</q> But this ſeems to grant, that if they were willingly reſigned to the <hi>care</hi> and <hi>power</hi> of a Chriſtian <hi>undertaker,</hi> they might be Baptized, and then the Church does not act againſt the <hi>Law of Nature;</hi> which is his <hi>fear</hi> and needleſſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> But he renewes his plea; <q rend="inline">[<hi>Then though there are none to educate this child, for the ignorant profane Parents will not but teach them how to break the Covenant; predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours cannot, they are dead, yet we muſt ſeal to this child</hi>]</q> Let the <hi>Church</hi> take it, and take <hi>care</hi> of it ſay we; But ſayes he, <q rend="inline">[<hi>Where do you ſee Churches take care of ſuch children, &amp;c.</hi>]</q> we anſwer, He need not go far to ſee this; he may perhaps ſee it in his own <hi>Pariſh.</hi> Our <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>State</hi> have ordered very commendably, and charitably, that the <hi>children</hi> of very <hi>Papiſts,</hi> are taken from them, and bred up Proteſtants. Yea every <hi>Pariſh</hi> is ordered to take care of their own poor <hi>Orphants.</hi> If they cannot, the <hi>State,</hi> with the <hi>charity</hi> of good men, hath provided <hi>Hoſpitals</hi> and <hi>Schooles</hi> for ſuch childrens education: we will put him a caſe. Suppoſe both the next Parents, being <hi>Church-members,</hi> dye, and leave <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants,</hi> having no known <hi>kindred</hi> in, or neer that place: who ſhall take care of them? we ſay the <hi>Church</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the Parents were members: for the children bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, are <hi>members</hi> of that Church, and the <hi>Church</hi> ought to take <hi>care</hi> of them. If the <hi>Congregational</hi> Church, neglect this, they come ſhort of our <hi>Paro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chial</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:118181:10"/> Churches, though they pretend not onely more <hi>piety,</hi> but more <hi>charity</hi> alſo to their own members. In a <hi>Christian Church</hi> or State, there ought to be a <hi>care</hi> of children, of Parents deceaſed, both in temporal and ſpiritual reſpects.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> And now we are come to the common objection. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>See ubi Suprae p.</hi> 212.</note> 
               <q rend="inline">[<hi>where ſhall we ſtay? how far may we go, for this prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor? how many generations? &amp;c.</hi>
               </q> This is fully an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered elſewhere: we onely once again deſire him to prove by <hi>expreſſe Scripture,</hi> that the promiſe <q rend="inline">[<hi>I will be thy God, and the God of thy ſeed,</hi>]</q> extends not onely to the <hi>next</hi> generation; or to how many generations it is limited. Something he ſpeaks to this purpoſe, pag. 28. <q rend="inline">[<hi>We find many promiſes made to the poſterity of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Parents,</hi> Gen. 17.7. <hi>&amp;c. now if the children of ſuch Parents grow up, and though but young, yet reading they find ſuch promiſes, or hear of them; it ſeems theſe poor children muſt not lay hold of the promiſe, and claime it by virtue of their parents, and plead it with God, &amp;c. for ſure if God will not ſo much as give them an outward ſeal of the Covenant, by virtue of the parent, the poor child cannot plead theſe promiſes, which come by the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent</hi>]</q> Thus he, and well, argued againſt the <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts.</hi> Do but but change the word <hi>parent</hi> into <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genitors,</hi> grandfather, or grandmother, and the plea is ſtrong againſt himſelf: Lord, I am ſure my <hi>grandfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> &amp;c. was a godly man, my <hi>grandmother,</hi> a godly woman; thou haſt made many promiſes to the <hi>poſterity</hi> of ſuch, not onely to the next, but as I think, <hi>remote</hi> ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations, though my <hi>next parents,</hi> were both wicked and profane; yet my <hi>pre-parents</hi> were godly. It ſeems, by this <hi>new</hi> Doctrine, to uſe his own words <q rend="inline">[<hi>This poor
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118181:11"/> child muſt not now go and lay hold of this promiſe, and ſpread it before God, &amp;c. for ſurely if God will not ſo much as give to this grandchild the outward ſeal of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant by virtue of the pro-parent, or grandfather, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not plead the promiſes, which come by him</hi>]</q> Let his own <hi>experience,</hi> in making uſe of theſe promiſes, teach him more <hi>mercy</hi> and <hi>charity</hi> to grandchildren.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> But he argues againſt us, thus: <q rend="inline">[<hi>If predeceſſours give right, then the children of an Immediate Parent Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiz'd from the faith, and excommunicated from the Church may be Baptized, &amp;c. and then the children of our</hi> Engliſh <hi>Apoſtates in</hi> Turky <hi>may be baptized, &amp;c.</hi>]</q> We fear not to affirm, they may, if either they will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign them up to thoſe that are <hi>Christians,</hi> their kindred or others, or any will <hi>undertake</hi> for their education. But in particular; Firſt, for the caſe of an <hi>Apoſtate,</hi> it is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered elſewhere, in the Diatrib. p. 188. And we add now, that an <hi>Apoſtate</hi> renouncing his <hi>Chriſtanity,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce alſo with it his Baptiſme, and ſo turns <hi>Heathen;</hi> and that alters the caſe, except, as afore, he be willing to give it up, to ſuch as will undertake for it. But then ſecondly, for the <hi>Excommunicate</hi> Parents (for if but one be a <hi>member,</hi> the child hath right to Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme) for ſuch Parents we ſay their <hi>caſe</hi> is not the ſame, with an <hi>Apostate,</hi> or <hi>Heathen:</hi> For though in ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, an <hi>Excommunicate</hi> perſon is <hi>worſe</hi> than an Infidel, (as the Apoſtle ſpeaks of a man that <hi>provides</hi> not for his family, though not excommunicated) becauſe he ſhould be better, &amp;c. yet in regard of State and <hi>Church-priviledges,</hi> he is better.</p>
            <p>For firſt, he is for <hi>ſtate</hi> ſtill a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> and retains his <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> which an <hi>Infidel</hi> hath not.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:118181:11"/>
            <p n="2">2. He is a <hi>members</hi> ſtill, though diſeaſed much, and a <hi>member</hi> under <hi>cure,</hi> (as the leper of old, ſhut out of the camp was) which an <hi>Infidel</hi> is not. He is I ſay, a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber in a large ſenſe, as he ſpeaks of a <hi>ſcandalous</hi> perſon tolerated, p. 41.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <q rend="inline">[<hi>Heathen and non-members of Churches, when they are taken into a Church, they are Baptized</hi>]</q> they are his own words, pag. 42. But ſo is not an <hi>Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate</hi> perſon, therefore his <hi>State</hi> is better than theirs; He is neither <hi>Heathen</hi> nor <hi>non-member: ergo</hi> a <hi>member</hi> at large.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, if in regard of <hi>Church-priviledges,</hi> he be no better than an <hi>Heathen,</hi> yet that is ſtill in <hi>reſpect</hi> to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, not to his child, who being born a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> of a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> hath <hi>right</hi> to Baptiſme, as ſhall appear in ſome <hi>caſes</hi> at leaſt. The child that is debarred <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> for the Parents <hi>Excommunication;</hi> falls into this puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, either when it is <hi>born</hi> before his <hi>Excommunication</hi> or after he is Excommunicated; If before his <hi>Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication</hi> it be born, but not <hi>Baptized</hi> before he is Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated, then his Excommunication cannot hinder its <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> for it is born a <hi>member</hi> of the Church, being born of one that was <hi>yet a member,</hi> when it was born: and the <hi>perſonal</hi> ſin of the Parent, cannot <hi>prejudice</hi> its right: (Baptiſme makes not a member, it was one before; as he ſpeaks pag. 25. of a <hi>Jewes</hi> child, a member before circumciſion) whence thus I argue upon his own principles; <q rend="inline">[<hi>A member of the Church, may be Baptized. But a child of a wicked, not yet excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, is born a member;</hi> ergo <hi>it may be Baptized</hi>]</q> though it ſhould happen (as it may) that it be not <hi>Baptized</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Excommunication. It remains then to ſay,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118181:12"/> either it loſes this <hi>right</hi> to Baptiſme, if it be born af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the <hi>parents</hi> Excommunication, or not at all. And now we are fallen upon his argument, p. 9. <q rend="inline">[<hi>If I may Baptize the child of an excommunicate perſon, then I may Baptize a child of a non-member of a Church, and ſo of an</hi> Indian <hi>or</hi> Turk, <hi>for they are non members, &amp;c. and he is no other, in reſpect of communion, in Church-priviledges</hi>]</q> we anſwer, by diſtinction of the Aſſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; I may Baptize the child of a Non-member, that is, of one that <hi>at preſent</hi> is accounted no member; as is plain in the caſe of a child <hi>born,</hi> but not baptized before the Parents Excommunicated. And therefore this <hi>conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence</hi> of his is unſound; <q rend="inline">[<hi>If the parent be a non-member, the child is a non-member alſo</hi>]</q> for that child is a member born, though the Parents at preſent ſtand Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated. It is true onely of an <hi>Infidel,</hi> or <hi>Apoſtate;</hi> who are no members: but an Excommunicate perſon, is in ſome ſence a <hi>member</hi> ſtill, as was ſaid above; and then to Baptize ſuch an one, is not to Baptize a <hi>Non-member.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> That <hi>Obſervation</hi> of Reverend <hi>Gilleſpy,</hi> from <hi>Buxtorf,</hi> &amp;c. is not very Orthodox, though <hi>true</hi> perhaps in the practice of the latter Jews: <q rend="inline">[<hi>That a child of an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate, ought not to be circumciſed</hi>]</q> It was, if done, a corrupt <hi>Invention,</hi> and <hi>Tradition</hi> of their own, of which there is no ground in Scripture. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, pag. 32. he does well to wave it.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> We ſhall not ſtand to vindicate thoſe holy and learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men, <hi>Zanchy,</hi> and <hi>Perkins,</hi> who plead for the <hi>Baptiſme</hi> of children of Parents Excommunicated, <hi>p.</hi> 11. That which hath been ſaid, may help towards it, we come to a new queſtion ſtarted, p. 13 <q rend="inline">[<hi>whether profeſsion of faith in Chriſt, though parents be groſly ignorant, ſcandalous,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118181:12"/> &amp;c, be ſufficient to make a man, and continue him a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the viſible Church:</hi>]</q> To which, we ſay in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, That our main <hi>queſtion</hi> is not about <hi>making</hi> or continuing a man a member of a Church, but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a man <hi>qualified</hi> as in the queſtion, continued and tolerated a member of the Church, can give right to to his childrens Baptiſme. And this he doth expreſly reſolve in the <hi>affirmative</hi> at leaſt three times. Once thus of a <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Parent wicked not excommunicated, <q rend="inline">[<hi>Doubtleſſe ſo long the immediate Parent was not caſt off from giving a right to his child, p.</hi> 13.]</q> Again, in the ſame pag <q rend="inline">[<hi>If a member be very ſcandalous, and the Church let him alone, that perſon may challenge any Ordinance in the Church, both Baptiſme and Lords Supper:</hi>]</q> Again pag. 34 <q rend="inline">[<hi>wicked perſons ſo long as they continue members, and the</hi> Church <hi>lets them alone, they may challenge Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme</hi>]</q> whence I would conclude the contradictory to his concluſion, in this manner. <q rend="inline">[<hi>The child of a ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous member tolerated, may be Baptized. But the child of a ſcandalous member not excommunicated, is the child of a ſcandalous member tolerated,</hi> ergo, <hi>it may be Baptized, and a miniſter may lawfully Baptize it.</hi>]</q> All he ſayes to this, is this, pag. 13. and 34, <q rend="inline">[<hi>Our queſtion is, whether ſuch perſons ſhould be let alone, is not that</hi> Church <hi>too blame?</hi>]</q> But by his favour, the queſtion is not, whether ſuch perſons ſhould be ſuffered, or the Church be too blame to ſuffer them: but whether ſuch being ſuffered in the Church, their children ought to be Baptized; and though he undertake the Negative, yet he determins the queſtion here Affirmatively: <q rend="inline">[<hi>So long as wicked perſons continue members, and the</hi> Church <hi>lets them alone, they may challenge Baptiſme.</hi>]</q> which
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:118181:13"/> one ſentence <hi>confutes,</hi> (as it contradicts) both his que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion and practice, in his refuſal to Baptize the children of ſuch; and at once gives us an anſwer to all his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments following: But we ſhall further conſider what he ſayes, to ſhew his miſtakes, and give him fuller ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15"/> The next undertaking is to prove, that ſuch (as in the queſtion) are not fit to be members; firſt thus: <q rend="inline">[<hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers are viſible Saints; but ſuch are not viſible Saints, ergo.</hi>]</q> 1. We muſt diſtinguiſh between a <hi>first admiſsion</hi> into a Church, and <hi>continuance</hi> in a Church, by ſuch as are born of members of a Church: Such, if now to be <hi>admitted,</hi> in their own perſons, are not fit to be members, nor ought to be admitted. But if children of members, prove <hi>ignorant</hi> or <hi>ſcandalous,</hi> they are to be continued, and accounted members, till they be le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally convicted, and caſt out: we grant ſuch a one, <q rend="inline">[<hi>is not qualified ſufficiently, to make a member, nor ought to be continued, continuing ſuch; but the</hi> Church <hi>ought to reform him, or eject him</hi>]</q> which are partly his own words. But then, while the Church is in reforming him, he is a <hi>member,</hi> and conſequently hath <hi>right</hi> to give his child Baptiſme. He ſhould have proved, (with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the firſt and main queſtion) that ſuch are not <hi>members,</hi> during the Churches <hi>toleration</hi> of them, and then infer, their children have no right, becauſe children of <hi>Non-members.</hi> 2. Church-members and viſible <hi>Saints,</hi> are taken in Scripture, ſometimes improperly; even ſuch as in the queſtion, <hi>ignorant, ſcandalous,</hi> &amp;c. are <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted,</hi> with the whole Church as Saints, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. &amp;c. and called <hi>brethren,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.11. 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.14,15. Now <hi>brethren</hi> and <hi>members</hi> are aequivalent terms; if
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:118181:13"/> they be accounted <hi>brethren,</hi> they may be accounted <hi>members,</hi> in a large ſenſe, as he confeſſeth pag. 41. 3. when we ſay a profeſſion of the faith is ſufficient to qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifie a man to be <hi>made</hi> or <hi>continued</hi> a member; we do not mean a bare <hi>profeſsion</hi> with his mouth, that he believes in <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> though viſibly he live like an <hi>Infidel;</hi> but thus at leaſt, when nothing in his life <hi>appears</hi> to the contrary<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, he ſeems to require no more, pag.</hi> 43.</note>; though there be yet no great <hi>poſitive ſignes</hi> of his holineſſe. Thus we think the <hi>Eunuch,</hi> at leaſt, <hi>Simon Magus</hi> was admitted. This indeed is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for <hi>Admiſsion;</hi> but as there muſt be more to <hi>continue</hi> ſuch in the Church, ſo there muſt be ſomething <hi>poſitive,</hi> of obſtinacy, in ignorance or groſſe wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in life, to <hi>caſt</hi> out again. The Church cannot up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Negative</hi> (if once admitted) caſt them out; nay, nor upon <hi>poſitive</hi> appearances, but after <hi>legal</hi> procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings with them; therefore ſo long, they are to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted members, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="16"/> Upon this ground, his ſecond argument pag. 14. falls alſo; <q rend="inline">[<hi>If (ſayes he) a bare profeſsion be ſufficient, then none can be caſt out for the vileſt ſins, Hereſie, &amp;c. becauſe he is the ſame now, as when he was admitted.</hi>]</q> The conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence is <hi>unſound,</hi> and proof like it. For when he was firſt <hi>admitted,</hi> upon his <hi>profeſsion,</hi> no ſuch <hi>ſcandal</hi> appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; but now it doth; therefore he is not the <hi>ſame,</hi> that he was, when admitted.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="17"/> The third Argument, is like the former, very weak, <q rend="inline">[<hi>A Rebel oppoſing Chriſt in his viſible Kingdom, is not fit to be a member of it, becauſe no ſubject;</hi>]</q> I anſwer, he is not fit to be <hi>admitted,</hi> if no member before; but fit to be <hi>continued</hi> till tryal of <hi>Reformation</hi> be paſt, and this himſelf confeſſeth after, pag. 17. of which here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:118181:14"/> A Rebel is a <hi>Subject,</hi> (though not an honeſt Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject) till reformed, or outlawed, or cut off. And we deſire to ſee the place in Scripture, where thoſe, who are within the <hi>outward Covenant,</hi> are preſently <hi>diſ-cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanted,</hi> if they walk contrary to the conditions of the Covenant.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="18"/> 
               <hi>Object.</hi> All are not convinced that Church-diſcipline is an Ordinance of God?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">[<hi>I ſpeak (ſaies he) of ſuch as have been convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and acknowledged it, from</hi> Matth. 18.15. <hi>but yet would not ſubmit to it</hi>]</q> Reply. Then ſay we, a man not <hi>convinced</hi> of it, may be a <hi>member,</hi> though he refuſe to ſubmit to diſcipline, if out of <hi>ignorance</hi> onely of this particular. But this <hi>qualification,</hi> is not in his queſtion; but generally, <q rend="inline">[<hi>If he refuſe to ſubject to Church-diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="19"/> To all his <hi>Authorities,</hi> Ancient and modern, pag. 15. &amp;c. That more then a <hi>bare profeſsion</hi> is required to make a <hi>member,</hi> we aſſent; but ſtill with our <hi>diſtinction,</hi> that more is required to the firſt <hi>admiſsion,</hi> than to the <hi>conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance</hi> of one born a member in the Church. And this leads us to that conſideration, of a <hi>Church</hi> to be <hi>now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted,</hi> &amp; one already <hi>constituted,</hi> p. 17. The Churches of <hi>England</hi> are not now in <hi>conſtituting,</hi> but a ſucceſſion for many years. To this he ſayes: <q rend="inline">[<hi>That which conſtitutes a Church, continues it a Church: if then, a bare profeſsion be not ſufficient to make a member, nor is it enough to continue a man a member of a Church.</hi>]</q> We anſwer, both <hi>propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> are faulty. The <hi>Minor,</hi> for we have proved, that a profeſſion of faith, nothing appearing to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, will conſtitute a member, and ſo a Church of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny members, though all hypocrites. The <hi>Major,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:118181:14"/> more is required to a firſt <hi>admiſsion;</hi> than to <hi>conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance</hi> in the Church. As is evident, in men of years converted from Infidels: a perſonal profeſſion of faith is neceſſary to ſuch: but their <hi>children</hi> are admitted, and continued without it, by their <hi>Birth priviledg,</hi> &amp;c. till they give evidences of their ignorance or ſcandal, and be orderly proceeded with, for their reformation. And this is his own reſolution and remedy to reform them without a new <hi>conſtitution,</hi> for ſo he ſayes: <q rend="inline">[<hi>Let Churches be conſtitute according to the rule, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued; or (mark it) exerciſe diſcipline, and reduce them to their firſt conſtitution</hi>]</q> This makes it clear, that there is another <hi>way</hi> to reform a conſtituted, but corrupted Church, than firſt to <hi>conſtitute</hi> a Church; viz. <hi>diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline.</hi> But then I would object.</p>
            <p n="1">1. How can we exerciſe <hi>diſcipline,</hi> (I ſay not where no <hi>Government</hi> is ſettled, but) when the parties refuſe to <hi>ſubmit</hi> to diſcipline, as not convinced of the <hi>Divine Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> of it?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Would he have men, <hi>ignorant</hi> or <hi>ſcandalous,</hi> or <hi>refuſers</hi> of diſcipline, ſuddenly ejected? Not ſo, he ſayes, <q rend="inline">[<hi>Not that I mean we fall preſently upon excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, before we have tryed other means, and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently waited.</hi>]</q> Well, then the perſon is yet a member, and the Church, a Church in being, or conſtituted (elſe no <hi>diſcipline</hi> could be exerciſed by it) though cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted: then have thoſe members <hi>under cure,</hi> right to all Ordinances for themſelves, and theirs: and ſo the Church needs no new conſtitution<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But if his arguing be good, our Churches are no true Churches, our <hi>mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers,</hi> no true members, for the greateſt part, having no <hi>right</hi> to Ordinances for themſelves, or theirs (why elſe
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:118181:15"/> are they <hi>debarred</hi> from both Sacraments) and ſo we are at once <hi>un-churched,</hi> and diſmembred, and a new <hi>frame</hi> to be moulded, which is flat <hi>Independentiſme, Browniſme,</hi> (if not <hi>Anabaptiſme</hi>) which this our <hi>Authour</hi> ſeems to have renounced.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> And now his arguments will be eaſily <hi>diſſolved.</hi> The firſt is this: <q rend="inline">[<hi>Such perſons (as the queſtion mentions) de jure ought, and de facto are excluded from the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, therfore they ought to be excluded from their childrens Baptiſme.</hi>]</q> Firſt, I deny the Antecedent, in the firſt part of it. Some of the <hi>perſons</hi> mentioned in the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, ought not <hi>de jure</hi> to be excluded from the <hi>Lords Supper;</hi> as namely, ſuch as <hi>refuſe to ſubmit to diſcipline,</hi> if godly, but not convinced yet of the divine <hi>Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> of diſcipline. This is nothing but the rigid way of the Independents, who exclude from the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> and Church-communion, thoſe that cannot <hi>ſubſcribe</hi> to their Church Covenant <hi>Explicite,</hi> be they never ſo god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and knowing, as was ſaid above. Secondly, all thoſe that the queſtion mentions, ought not to be excluded from the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> while they are tolerated in the Church. This is his own <hi>confeſsion</hi> often: and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently ought not to be excluded from their childrens Baptiſme. Then for the latter part, that they are <hi>de facto</hi> excluded, admits a queſtion, whether they are not unjuſtly excluded. And it is reſolved to be ſo, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by Mr. <hi>Jeans</hi> his arguments; but as a <hi>conſequence</hi> of the former: If <hi>de jure,</hi> they ought not to be excluded, then <hi>de facto,</hi> they are <hi>unjustly</hi> excluded: which is worthy all Miniſters conſideration, who for many years have had no <hi>Sacraments</hi> for fear of admitting ſuch, as the <hi>queſtion</hi> mentions: whereby, pretending
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:118181:15"/> they <hi>want</hi> power of an <hi>Elderſhip,</hi> no <hi>Government</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſettled, they uſurp (inconſiderately perhaps) a power <hi>above</hi> the Elderſhips to exclude, not onely ſuch, but their whole Pariſh, by their own <hi>ſingle</hi> power: But ſee into what ſtreights the <hi>New way</hi> hath brought us? They cryed out of our <hi>Churches,</hi> and ſeparated from them, becauſe of our <hi>mixt communions;</hi> And now <hi>Miniſters</hi> abſtaining from the adminiſtration of the <hi>Supper,</hi> for fear of a <hi>mixture;</hi> they cry out again, and call people to ſeparate from us, becauſe we <hi>want</hi> an Ordinance. The Lord judge between us in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. But now for the conſequence, <q rend="inline">[<hi>that therefore they ought to be excluded from their childrens Baptiſme;</hi>]</q> it is alſo denyed, and all the proofs thereof. For it ſhould proceed of the ſame, not of <hi>ſeveral</hi> perſons, thus; Thoſe that <hi>de jure</hi> ought, and <hi>de facto</hi> are exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> ought (if now they were to be Baptized) alſo to be excluded from Baptiſme for themſelves. As backward, if excluded juſtly from Baptiſme, much more from the Lords Supper. But it holds not with reſpect to their children; (as we have heard by his own confeſſion.) The young <hi>children</hi> of members, are unfit to be admitted to the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> yet not to be excluded from Baptiſme. The reaſon is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe more is required to the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> then to their Baptiſme. The proof is as weak, as the conſequence; <q rend="inline">[<hi>Baptiſme ſeals to the ſame Covenant, as the Lords Supper doth</hi> ergo, <hi>if excluded from one they ought to be exclud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d from the other.</hi>]</q> It holds good againſt themſelves, not their children. The proofe of this is like the former; <q rend="inline">[<hi>The ground of excluſion from both, is the ſame,</hi> viz: <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thoſe perſons appear not ſuch, as to whom thoſe pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges do belong:</hi>]</q> this is falſe in reſpect to their
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:118181:16"/> children: And all theſe conſequences are grounded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his firſt (falſe) premiſed ſuppoſition, at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; <hi>viz.</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">[<hi>that the child hath no right, but in relation to the next Parent</hi>]</q> which is confuted above. And now we add briefly. 1. Its <hi>Birth-priviledge,</hi> that being born a Chriſtian of a Chriſtian gives it right, as of old to circumciſion. 2. It may have right from a <hi>grandfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> or by adoption, &amp;c. 3. Neither the <hi>Scripture</hi> nor any <hi>Hiſtory</hi> (that we remember) gives an <hi>inſtance,</hi> that the perſonal <hi>default</hi> of a Chriſtian Parent Baptized, ever hindred the <hi>child</hi> from Baptiſme. 4. Himſelf con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futes his own argument, by often granting, that ſuch (as in the queſtion) <hi>tolerated</hi> by the Church, have right for themſelves and theirs: Let him conſider it.</p>
            <p>Whereupon, his <hi>obſervation</hi> pag. 19. of admitting the children to <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> in the <hi>afternoone,</hi> whoſe <hi>Parents</hi> in the morning were excluded from the <hi>Supper,</hi> need not ſeem ſo ſtrange, and his <hi>Dilemma</hi> may be retorted upon himſelf, thus: He grants, a wicked perſon tolerated, may be admitted to the Lords Supper, and his child to Baptiſme; onely he ſayes, <hi>de jure</hi> he ought to be exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Now I would ask, (as he) does ſuch a man ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to be under the Covenant of Grace or no? If ſo, why ſhould he <hi>de jure</hi> be excluded? If not, why ſhould he, <hi>de facto,</hi> be admitted? or why does he give <hi>Baptiſme</hi> to the childe, which (ſayes he) muſt ſuppoſe the Parent to be within the Covenant? So here is a <hi>believer,</hi> and no believer, in a ſhort time, and yet the <hi>ſame</hi> man. Let him anſwer one, and both.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="21"/> He grants <hi>Suſpenſion</hi> from the Lords Supper, in ſome ſence; pag. 19. of one fallen into ſome <hi>groſſe</hi> ſin: and I think, he does not deny Baptiſme to the children of ſuch, which if he yield, he deſtroyes his own argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:118181:16"/> and queſtion. As for his <hi>Quaere,</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">[<hi>whether if the parent be ſuſpended from the Supper, his child may not alſo be ſuſpended for the preſent, till he repent, being the child depends on the Parent, &amp;c.</hi>]</q> may be thus anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, by his own principles: The Parent, though ſuſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from the Supper, is yet a Church-member, till he be <hi>Excommunicated,</hi> then hath he <hi>right</hi> to give his child Baptiſme. If the <hi>Parents</hi> ſin, did annul his own Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme or render him an <hi>Heathen</hi> again, it were a queſtion whether it did not hinder his childes Baptiſme. But ſuſpenſion does not that, nor excommunication but ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Apoſtacy onely: Beſides, it would be proved, that that which ſuſpends from one priviledge ſuſpends from all: and that for his child, as well as for himſelf. The child (we ſay) having a <hi>native right,</hi> it ſeems unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and injurious, that the Parents <hi>perſonal</hi> fault, ſhould ſuſpend it. Elſe in this caſe there is no difference, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the child of a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> and of an <hi>Infidel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="22"/> The next argument proceeds thus. <q rend="inline">[<hi>Such Parents, if they were now to be Baptized, ought not to be Baptized;</hi> ergo, <hi>cannot challenge it for their children. The reaſon is, becauſe Baptiſme belongs primarily to the Parent, if</hi> ergo, <hi>he have no right, he can give none</hi>]</q> The conſequence is again denyed, and the proof of it;</p>
            <p>For firſt, it a received <hi>Maxime</hi> amongſt the Lawyers; <hi>Quod fieri non debuit, factum valet.</hi> Suppoſe an unfit perſon Baptized, his Baptiſme is not null, he is a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber till <hi>legally</hi> excluded, and ſo hath right for himſelf and his, to the <hi>conſequent</hi> priviledges.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He <hi>confutes</hi> this argument alſo, by granting, a wicked member tolerated, to have right to all Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; yet if he were now to be Baptized, he ought not ſo to be accounted.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:118181:17"/>
            <p n="3">3. His reaſon is of no force: for it ſhould thus pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, becauſe Beptiſme belongs, both <hi>primarily,</hi> and <hi>onely</hi> to the next parent, which we have above denyed, and diſproved. In a word; this argument holds onely in reſpect to the <hi>perſon</hi> himſelf, not to his <hi>child.</hi> For certainly the child that is Baptized when an <hi>Infant,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the child of a member, had right to Baptiſme then, though if when it growes up, it proves <hi>ignorant</hi> or <hi>ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous,</hi> we may truly ſay, if he were now to be Baptized, he ought not to be Baptized. Hence it may appear, that the queſtion will fall onely upon ſuch perſons when <hi>Excommunicate,</hi> which yet is no <hi>qualification,</hi> expreſſed in his queſtion: For till they are ejected, they have right (by his own confeſsion) for himſelf and theirs. But of <hi>Excommunicate</hi> Perſons, we have ſpoken above.</p>
            <p>The third argument is like the former: <q rend="inline">[<hi>Such a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, is no diſciple,</hi> ergo, <hi>the child is none: and then Miniſters are not bound to baptize it, by their Commiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>]</q> we anſwer, 1. That <hi>Commiſsion</hi> was for the firſt <hi>gathering</hi> of Churches; not of <hi>Churches</hi> conſtituted; 2. We have proved above, the child may be a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, when the Parent at <hi>preſent</hi> is none, being <hi>Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated.</hi> Now a <hi>diſciple</hi> and a <hi>member,</hi> is all one. 3. Such <hi>Parents</hi> tolerated are members, and ſo diſciples; <hi>ergo,</hi> the child is a diſciple. That then is not a ſound aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, pag. 20. <q rend="inline">[<hi>If I can give the child one ſeal of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, by virtue of the Parent, I will give the Parent the other</hi>]</q> for I may ſee reaſon to deny the Parent the Lords Supper, and yet Baptize his child: becauſe more is required of the one, than of the other.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="24"/> His fourth Argument runs thus: <q rend="inline">[<hi>To give the ſeal to the child of one viſibly in Covenant with the Devil, is a
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:118181:17"/> profaning of the Ordinance, &amp;c.</hi>]</q> But we deny that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ignorant, ſcandalous perſon, and the reſt in the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, is viſibly in Covenant with the devil; eſpecially if <hi>tolerated</hi> by the Church, for ſo long he is viſibly in the <hi>external Covenant</hi> of the Church. 2. Suppoſe the perſon be <hi>Excommunicate,</hi> and ſo delivered unto <hi>Satan,</hi> (as the <hi>incestuous</hi> perſon was) yet it were hard to ſay, he were <hi>viſibly</hi> in Covenant with <hi>Satan,</hi> though at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent under his power. 3. Every groſſe ſin (as in <hi>Noah, David,</hi> &amp;c.) does not conclude a man <hi>viſibly</hi> in Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Diatrib.</hi> p. 190</note> much leſſe <hi>ignorance,</hi> as in children and youths Baptized. 2. Laſt of all, one not <hi>convinced,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not ſubmitting unto <hi>diſcipline.</hi> See whether this new way leads its followers.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="25"/> His fifth argument is taken from <hi>miſchiefs</hi> attending the common Baptizing of the children of ſuch; <q rend="inline">[1. <hi>The ſlighting of this Ordinance; without any preparation to it.</hi>]</q> But all this may be amended by preſſing the due reverence to this, as to the other Sacrament; better then by debarring the child its right, for the Parents fault. 2. <q rend="inline">[<hi>Its a jumbling of the children of the moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with the profaneſt, &amp;c.</hi>]</q> This falls upon himſelf; For if the wicked Parents be <hi>tolerated,</hi> he will not, he may not deny to Baptize their children; no more, than of the holieſt Parent. He may grieve that he cannot reform this abuſe, but need not <hi>ſcruple</hi> to Baptize their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; nor to <hi>pray</hi> for them, as for the other.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="26"/> And now he comes to the great objection; <q rend="inline">[<hi>The Jews, though very wicked, had their children circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,</hi> ergo.]</q> He anſwers many wayes.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He mentions again that obſervation of <hi>Gilleſpy,</hi> that ſome ſaid, <q rend="inline">[<hi>that the children of Excommunicated
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:118181:18"/> Jews were not circumciſed</hi>]</q> But he does well to wave it; as for what we ſaid to it above; ſo becauſe it is nothing to the queſtion, which is not of <hi>excommunicated</hi> pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, but wicked Parents <hi>tolerated.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <q rend="inline">[<hi>He ſuppoſes they were not ſo guilty of ignorance, as many of ours.</hi>]</q> But thats nothing to the queſtion; their children were as <hi>ignorant</hi> as ours, and the Parents never <hi>Excommunicated</hi> for ignorance, nor their children denyed <hi>circumciſion</hi> for that reaſon. But cloſer to the point he ſayes.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He would ſee a proof, <q rend="inline">[<hi>that the Prieſts did debar many from the Paſſeover, for moral uncleanneſs, many years, as ours do from the Supper, and yet had their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren circumciſed</hi>]</q> We anſwer. 1. The Prieſts are blamed for admitting the morally unclean, to ſome Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, but it concerns him to prove, where ever they were blamed, for circumciſing the children of ſuch. See <hi>Ezech.</hi> 44.7.9. cited by himſelf, pag. 35. to the ſame end. 2. It is doubtful at leaſt, whether the practiſe of thoſe miniſters can be juſtified, who <hi>ſuſpend</hi> any ſo long from the <hi>Supper,</hi> and yet Baptize their children: therefore that can be no <hi>ſafe ground</hi> to debar children of ſuch from Baptiſme: Of which ſee Mr. <hi>Jeanes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. He conceives <q rend="inline">[<hi>Something peculiar to them, in that National conſtitution, from ours: Gods enters Covenant with Abraham, and his family; commands him to cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſe his ſeed: the conſtitution of our Churches, does not begin with any particular perſon; but makes diſciples, and Baptize them</hi>]</q> But this makes no great difference: For a Church Chriſtian may begin with a perſon and his familie; Suppoſe one of a <hi>numerous family,</hi> when he is diſcipled, his houſe is diſcipled with him; and there may be a <hi>Church</hi> in his houſe; yea every <hi>houſhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:118181:18"/> converted to the faith, was a <hi>child</hi> of <hi>Abraham,</hi> in one ſenſe; and a <hi>root</hi> to his poſterity in another, and ſo the promiſe is made to him and his ſeed, not onely of the <hi>next,</hi> but of remoter generations, till they Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, as <hi>Iſhmael</hi> and <hi>Eſau</hi> did: He yields pag. 33. that deſcent by the fleſh, was one, though not the <hi>ſole</hi> ground of circumciſion. And ſo it is now, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14. Let us ſee what was peculiar to them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <q rend="inline">[<hi>When they came to Johns Baptiſme, it was not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to plead, we are Abrahams ſeed,</hi> ergo, <hi>Baptize us.</hi>]</q> True, becauſe this was a new diſpenſation, a <hi>new Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance,</hi> to which <hi>repentance</hi> was required in the firſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, but not of their <hi>Infants.</hi> And juſt ſo it was in <hi>Circumciſion</hi> of Proſelytes, to the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Religion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <q rend="inline">[<hi>When they fell to foul Apoſtacy, their children were ſtill Circumciſed, whether regularly, he leaves it.</hi>]</q> Yes <hi>regularly,</hi> for ought appears to the contrary: The Rule was, <q rend="inline">[<hi>Abraham and his ſeed muſt be circumciſed.</hi>]</q> And ſo the <hi>proportion</hi> holds for Baptiſm. If the parents fall into <hi>Apoſtacy,</hi> the children may regularly be baptiz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for ought appears in the Goſpel to the contrary, if they will give them up to their <hi>pro-parents</hi> or friends, and they will <hi>undertake</hi> for them. And in ſuch a caſe a <hi>Miniſter</hi> would Baptize them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <q rend="inline">[<hi>They were very exact in admiſsion of Heathens: more required, than to profeſſe they did believe in God, &amp;c.</hi>]</q> So would we be, in admiſſion of <hi>Infidels:</hi> but thats nothing to admiſſion of their children.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="28"/> 
               <q rend="inline">[<hi>It is true, that wicked Jews being members of that Church National, might challenge circumciſion, ſo for wicked perſons, ſo long as they continue members, and the Church lets them alone, they may challenge Baptiſme.</hi>]</q> Now this expreſly yields both the preſent argument,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:118181:19"/> from the <hi>Jews,</hi> to be good: and alſo the <hi>main queſtion,</hi> that ſuch perſons, if <hi>tolerated,</hi> may give right to their childrens Baptiſme, and <hi>Miniſters</hi> not onely may, but are bound to Baptize them, againſt which he hath all this while diſputed. Onely he ſayes; <q rend="inline">[<hi>Our queſtion is, whether ſuch perſons ſhould be let alone? is not that Church too blame? ought ſuch</hi> de jure <hi>to be members?</hi>]</q> No, the queſtion was, whether ſuch perſons, while <hi>ſuffered</hi> in the Church, have right to give their children Baptiſme? And that is fully granted.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="29"/> For more <hi>exactneſſe in the Churches of the Goſpel,</hi> in divers reſpects, we diſſent not, ſo it be not beyond the <hi>Rule.</hi> But as he diſlikes the <hi>rigidneſſe,</hi> which ſome (he means the Independents) would have, in <hi>admiſsion</hi> of members, to Church-communion, ſo we diſlike his <hi>ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gidneſſe,</hi> in admiſsion of <hi>children</hi> to Baptiſme.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> All that diſcourſe concerning the <hi>ſenſe</hi> of 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.11. for many pages together, I purpoſely paſſe by, as lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into another <hi>controverſie.</hi> I ſhall onely conſider, that <hi>Queſtion</hi> propounded, pag. 42. as his <hi>Advice</hi> for the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation</hi> of our Congregations, which is this; <q rend="inline">[<hi>Whether it were not better for the Miniſters of</hi> England, <hi>as they do ſuſpend perſons from the Lords Supper, ſo alſo for a time to ſuſpend them from Baptizing their children, and in the mean time, Ministers to follow Catechizing cloſe, &amp;c?</hi>]</q> To which I have theſe things to ſay.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It proceeds upon an erroneous, at leaſt a <hi>doubtful</hi> practice, that <hi>Miniſters</hi> have done <hi>well,</hi> in ſuſpending ſo long, ſuch men, their <hi>whole Pariſhes,</hi> from the <hi>Lords Supper;</hi> of which ſomething hath been ſaid above. This way as it hath given occaſion to ſome to <hi>ſeparate,</hi> and joyn themſelves to <hi>Independent</hi> Churches, as want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with us an Ordinance; ſo it hath made others
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:118181:19"/> more <hi>profane</hi> than before, who were ſomething <hi>awed,</hi> by their <hi>approaches</hi> to that Sacrament.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For the <hi>Inference</hi> from that practice; I ſay, If they did, and do well, in <hi>ſuſpending</hi> ſuch from the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, yet it is not ſafe or expedient (in my judgment) to ſuſpend them from the other, for their <hi>children,</hi> as things now ſtand in <hi>England:</hi> for beſides what hath been ſaid, in behalf of poor <hi>children</hi> above, I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve.</p>
            <p n="1">1. If one <hi>Baptize</hi> them not, another of another Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhall, and will, and who can hinder it? This in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth the <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>viſions</hi> betwixt miniſters, by others in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termedling within their <hi>charges,</hi> and Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This will be one way, to make the next <hi>generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> no better than <hi>Infidels,</hi> for the moſt part, being all unbaptized; or elſe profane and ignorant, as being without the <hi>care</hi> of the Churches.</p>
            <p n="3">3. This will <hi>exaſperate</hi> the Parents, being <hi>profane</hi> and deſperate enough already, againſt their <hi>Miniſters,</hi> and ſo not onely <hi>prejudice</hi> them in their maintenance (how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he findes it otherwiſe by the power of ſome friends) but alſo <hi>alienate</hi> their minds more from the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired Reformation.</p>
            <p n="4">4. This is contrary to the expreſſe <hi>Rule,</hi> to puniſh the poor children for the Parents <hi>perſonal</hi> faults; at leaſt in ſome caſes, as is manifeſted above.</p>
            <p n="5">5. This is contrary to his own <hi>principles,</hi> who hath often granted, that while ſuch Parents (as in the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion) are ſuffered in the Church, they have right for themſelves and theirs, <q rend="inline">[<hi>and you muſt not deny it, if you own them for Church-members, however custome hath
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:118181:20"/> prevailed to the excluſion of them from it, without regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar proceeding, &amp;c.</hi>]</q> pag. 42. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>If the Church ſhall tolerate ſuch evils, &amp;c. they cannot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny them the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledg of mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, Survey, part</hi> 3. p. 11. <hi>and he inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in the Church of Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis, &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> Now both Mr. <hi>Hooker,</hi> Survey, part 3. pag. 11. and himſelf hath often yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them to be members to all priviledges of the Church, while (ſinfully) tolerated. And as for that <hi>regular</hi> proceeding to reform them by ſuſpenſion, or eject them by Excommunication, it is not in the power of any <hi>Miniſter</hi> alone, and therefore not onely <hi>unjust</hi> if they ſhould uſurp it, but alſo impoſsible, as our <hi>Churches</hi> yet ſtand, for the moſt part, <hi>unpreſbytered,</hi> and without a ſettled Government. Whence a new ground of <hi>obloquie</hi> and reproach, would be offered to <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptists</hi> and <hi>Independents,</hi> yea and to profane people too, to charge our <hi>Churches,</hi> at leaſt our <hi>Miniſters</hi> as <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian,</hi> for uſurping not onely a <hi>Biſhop-like,</hi> but a <hi>Pope-like</hi> power in every Pariſh; the thing ſo much fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the <hi>Preſbytery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="31"/> What remains then, but that it were a better way to reform our Congregations; if the <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> could be prevailed with, to ſettle a right Government in the Church, which all <hi>Congregations</hi> ſhould be bound to ſubmit to, or elſe to execute <hi>Juſtice</hi> upon notorious Offendors, and ſcandalous perſons; the Miniſters in the mean time, <q rend="inline">[<hi>following Catechizing cloſe, to breed knowledg in their people, and labouring to reform them from a ſcandalous converſation, by all the gentle perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and meekneſſe of wiſdom, which God ſhall give them:</hi>]</q> that ſo, when the <hi>Authority</hi> of the Magiſtrate hath civillized at leaſt their converſation, and by <hi>Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chizing,</hi> they have gotten knowledg, we may then with more comfort give them the priviledge of both the Ordinances. In the mean time, (ſuch are the
<pb facs="tcp:118181:20"/> ſtraits ſome men have brought us into) no better way (in my ſhallow head) than to preſſe hard upon ſuch Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, the conditions of the Covenant of grace, at the times of Baptiſme, or other times, the <hi>duties</hi> of Parents with reſpect to their own Baptiſme, and their childrens; as by this ſeal, <hi>engaged</hi> both of them to be <hi>Gods people,</hi> that is, <q rend="inline">[<hi>to know him, to fear him, to love him, to truſt in him, to delight in him, and to obey him in all his holy commands delivered in the Word;</hi>]</q> and all this, as they expect the <hi>performance</hi> of the <hi>Covenant</hi> on Gods part, <hi>to be their God.</hi> By all which faithfully and earneſtly preſſed upon them, they may, (by the bleſsing of God, upon our labours) be <hi>qualified</hi> according to his own Rules, delivered in his <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> by which he practices; viz. <q rend="inline">[1. <hi>See and profeſs the ſenſe of their own undone condition by ſin, and utter inability to help themſelves; but by relying upon Chriſt.</hi> 2. <hi>Have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent knowledg.</hi> 3. <hi>Have their converſation ſuch, as doth not croſs their profeſsion, by living in any known ſin, or omitting any known duty, as praying and Catechiſing in their families, &amp;c. And laſtly, profeſs (if it be neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry) their ſubjection to diſcipline;</hi>]</q> to tye them faſter by a new obligation, to a duty, to which they were bound before, by their <hi>Covenant</hi> of Chriſtianity.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
